the first thing I want to talk about is
is the bench height so I've always done
um hip thrust off of a with my back on a
bench but uh some of the benches uh you
know I had a lower bench in in my garage
and it it was very conducive to hip
thrust and if you look at my first hip
thrust video the one that you know has
over 100,000 views and got really
popular my torso angle is when my butt's
on the ground my torso angle is at
around a 45 degree angle but you see
some of the bench Heights are really
high and you see some of the people's
torso angles are almost vertical that's
I don't like it going that deep um some
people can make their back feel weird I
prefer a lower bench height and uh I've
been doing this for a while and I like
using an aerobic step here I have two
risers um but I like three risers I like
four risers but in between that range um
so I feel the most glute activation when
I go around this height three three
risers is probably my preference and the
next thing I want to talk about is back
position and uh I just hook it if I were
to be doing single leg you kind of hook
in this is exactly where I want it right
here you don't as you do the hip thrust
you don't want to be sliding backwards
on it you want to hinge from here so I
stick if I choose right here I come up
and I stick I hinge around that point so
you find a comfortable back position and
that's where you stay you don't want to
slide up and down and glide over and
you're
hinging okay now I'm going to talk about
bar position so the way I get the bar
into position and this is possible
because I use the larger plates if you
don't if you're not strong enough to use
larger plates you can't do this but I
just roll it over you know I put my legs
under it and I roll it over
and I just get it right in my lower
abdominal region so this is right above
my pubic bone and then on here it's
touching my hip flexors so I'm not
resting on bone right now and I come up
to
here I feel it touching lower abdomen
upper hip flexor
musculature now some people aren't as
lucky as me they it on bone maybe
they're not as mus muscled or they're
they have different you know pelvic
Anatomy but if that's the case you will
benefit from using padding there's two
scenarios one is the Hampton thick
barpad see how thick the padding is here
this works well and I train a bunch of
girls right now some of them prefer the
Hampton thick bar pad and some of them
prefer the ERX balance pad um it just
comes down to per personal preference I
like the aex balance pad because you can
use it for more things but with the
Hampton thick bar pad you place it
through and then you want to make sure
that when I roll it onto my hips that
this crease is facing upwards because if
I if I have the crease facing downwards
it'll come through the slit and then
it's resting on your your body and you
don't have the Patty so if you use the
hand the bar pad make sure when you get
it into position the slit is facing
upwards but when you use the Eric's
balance pad I just kind of go like this
and then you know roll it into place
this way and just like
that okay when you do get the VAR into
position my foot
placement I have a slight foot flare
some people like their feet straight
ahead some people like more of a flare
again this is down to personal
preference I like a slight foot
flare and uh you kind of when you get
into place you kind of screw your body
into place get tight you know my back is
secure my feet are secure I feel stable
now at this point as I press up my hands
just go on top of the barbell to guide
it and keep it into position you don't
want the bar rolling back or down during
this during the rep so it stays into
position so watch watch the bar up top
here it stays right there I don't let it
roll back and I don't push it Forward
stays right here the whole set it
doesn't
move one last thing neck position I
don't think this is too important but
just try to keep your neck I'm sure I
flex a lot but you know you can some
people like to put their head back on
the bench I don't think this is is that
important try and keep it in neutral
throughout this set so you know maybe
tuck the chin so as you come up the neck
the head and neck kind of travel with
the
body okay the next thing I'm going to
talk about is uh is spinal and and
pelvic um motion uh when when you do
this exercise
so uh this is the main compensation
pattern the main way that people screw
up a hip thrust and the hip thrust can
be dangerous just like any other
exercise can be dangerous if you
deadlift with a rounded back in lumbar
flexion you will eventually hurt your
low back if you hip thrust with a
hyperextended position over and over
repeatedly for many years you will
probably hurt your back and so you want
to avoid that well here's an easy way to
tell so you
want the motion revolving
around the hip joint right through here
and you want this to stay straight well
when you watch people do hip thrust the
wrong way they will you watch their
chest come up you see this towards the
end of a set a lot of times and you have
to get people to build up the discipline
to keep their their their torso you know
uh in neutral while they use the glutes
to push their hips up so if you watch
here here I will do it the correct way
watch my torso so all the
motion occurs through the hip
joint if I hyp extend my lumbar spine
you will see this is what you'll
see see that do you see this Arch okay
so if they do it the right way this
stays neutral now what about the pelvis
so if you come up and I'm see this this
this is pelvic posterior tilt interior
tilt posterior tilt interior
tilt and the pelvis and the spine work
together um that's why they call and the
hips too they call it the lumbopelvic
hip complex so if I let the spine go
into anterior pelvic tilt I'm probably
going to hyperextend my lumbar spine so
you want to use the glutes as not only
hip extensors but posterior pelvic
tilters or probably more accurately anti
anterior pelvic tilters what I mean is
you don't let the pelvis go into
anterior tilt so as I come
up this is anterior tilt posterior tilt
inter tilt poster tilt
so see this motion this is pelvic motion
I know it kind of looks funny but the
body under load wants to do this you're
using your glutes to prevent that from
happening so if you just push through
the hips and focus on not allowing that
okay you won't be able to come up quite
as high because posterior tilt actually
mimics hip extension um so you have two
choices here push the glutes up really
high into hip
hyperextension or kind of poster your
tilt as you come up and you won't be
able to come up quite as high either in
a way I think is equally as valid um but
the posterior pelvic tilt option really
prevents that lumbar spine from
hyperextending and I had a couple
clients um over the last year who
initially they said Brett I feel this in
my low back I said try it this way with
the posterior pelvic tilt it's just
slight posterior pelvic tilt they have
never had a problem with hip thrust ever
since okay the next thing I want to talk
about is um is
fluidity fluidity and full range of
motion so so I've watched these videos
of people doing hip thrust on the
internet some of them are really done
well and some of them are poorly if you
watch someone in there like
this that's um just as bad as a quarter
squat or a you know a crappy round back
deadlift you want to make sure the hips
are controlling the range of motion it
needs to look fluid and this is just
something you get an eye for so watch
this see how how fluid this looks and I
use a full range of motion there's no
partial reps so here's what it looks
like I'll do three
reps that was fluid the whole
time I can be explosive but my glutes
feel it up top I don't let tension off
that's the most important thing get
people doing it fluidly throughout the
whole range and don't let them go too
heavy to where they can't do that and
then build them up slowly and gradually
over time so they don't start cheating
make sure you always achieve a full
range of
motion all right now I'm going to go
over the seven different types of
barbell hip thrust variations the first
one I just call the barbell glute Bridge
because you're not elevating anything
the barbell glute bridge I am just going
to keep my shoulders right here on the
ground just do it like this
um my only problem with the Barbo glute
bridge is that if I do it on you know
some rubber flooring I stick but if the
if the flooring is you know is uh like
wood or tile or something you slide all
around so really helps to do it on a a
surface with a lot of friction otherwise
I try and have some someone stand you
know facing um backwards or something
and I put my shoulders up against their
the back of their legs and that prevents
me from sliding
backwards um I like the barell glute
Bridge it's less range of motion but you
can use heavier loads so quid proquo
there okay the next variation is just
the regular hip thrust and again you can
Elevate this however you want but the
regular hip thrust is with my my back
right here and this is the traditional
hip
thrust just like that and my my
shoulders hinge the next
variation I'll call the American hip
thrust but I actually I had never
thought of this until I saw Timothy
Ferris uh came up with it and he was
doing hip thrust like this with his his
back way up on
here and you just go like
this and I don't know why I don't do
more of this American hip thrust because
I actually think it works more glute and
I think if I were to test the glute
activation I would show higher higher
higher um EMG with the American hip
thrust you can also use heavier loads in
fact you know I can do you know 500 lb
for like eight reps this way and when I
finish my glutes are so pumped you know
I I have hard time walking correctly so
don't uh underestimate the American hip
thrust the difference is just where my
where the my back is hinging against the
uh bench so I like it cuz you can also
kind of place your elbows right here see
my elbows stay on top of the bench and
you just kind of from here
just so that's the American hip thrust
very good variation that you should do
from time to time lets you go a little
bit heavier too all right now the next
variations are just variations with the
way you do your
set and one of them is the rest paw the
rest Paw I'm going to do with heavy
weight say I've got you know 450 lb on
the bar and I can do it for like five
reps well I will do my five you know one
2 3 four five and then I'm going to rest
like it doesn't matter there's no rules
set in stone but I'll rest 10 seconds 1
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 do another rep okay
rest 10 more seconds do another back
okay this is a a way to extend the set
and I like to think it works more on the
neural side of the the neuromuscular
system but maybe I'm just making that up
but anyway it's a it's an advanced
method that lets you extend the set and
lets you get more repetitions with heavy
heavy weight all right the next method
is the constant tension method with the
constant tension method I like to load
the plates up um with with females
especially
with uh like 25 lb plates because you
can see this is actually 100 lb plate
right here but um see how there's
tension down low because the bar is
maintaining contact so I have tension
all the way at the bottom but with some
women they don't have tension you want
tension throughout the whole range and I
don't even even let them touch they just
kind of I I'll put the bar in their lap
up top and you just pump them out like a
piston so with the constant tension is
just kind of like this you'll just
go and you're just focused on just think
of a piston going up down up down up
down and uh this gets an incredible burn
when I do the conent tension method I
only use 225 lbs for 20 reps and it
kills me all right the next method is
the pause method and with the pause
method I just do a 3 second pause up top
and um this is
provides a really unique stimulus it
really Burns um my female clients really
love this method is a just for variety
but all you do here is count to 3
seconds up top if you tell people on
their own count to 3 seconds up top they
really do 1 second but you're going to
really hold it 3 seconds so come
up one 2
3 one two three okay I've found that you
can usually get about 10 reps with what
you can normally do for about 30 reps
that way and uh then the last method I
want to show you is the iso hold method
and uh this you just come up to the top
hold it for
time lock yourself in right here don't
let your spine move into hyperextension
squeeze the glutes the whole way and you
just hold
it and you know I've done like 405 for
I think 25 or 30 seconds that way and it
is brutal so anyway those are the seven
different ways of doing bilateral
barbell hip thrust variations